A Guide to the Papers of the Jones Family of Louisa County, Va., 1853-1908
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Jones Family of Louisa County, Va. 1853-1908
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13407
This collection consists of ca. 154 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These letters were a gift from Mrs. Benjamin F. Harmon, 9300 University Blvd., Richmond, Va. on September 14, 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Most of the collection consists of letters from three brothers who fought in the "Louisa Blues" 13th Regiment of Virginia in the Confederate Army (1861 to 1863) to their family in Louisa Court House, Virginia. The brothers were the Reverend John William Jones (1836-1909), Phillip Edloe Jones (n.y.-1863) and Francis Pendleton Jones (1840-1863). They saw action in the Shenandoah Valley Campaign of Stonewall Jackson. Phillip Edloe Jones was wounded in battle (shot in the lungs) and died at home in Louisa Courthouse in February of 1863. His mother, Ann Pendleton Ashby Jones, died on September 23,1862 while caring for her son, Edloe. Francis Pendleton Jones was wounded in the Battle of Gettysburg and died on September 2, 1863 in Winchester, Virginia. Their letters reveal their distinct personalities as well as details of the Civil War. Edloe loved soldier life and reveled in the comraderie, discipline and strenuous physical demands of camp. Pendleton was a free spirit who became a first- rate cook, adapted well to camp life and enjoyed being a part of his regiment. John (the Reverend John William Jones) graduated from the University of Virginia and as the oldest of the brothers gave them advice on their studies and career paths. During the war he took comfort in his religion and service to others. Edloe Jones was the leader among his brothers in soldier life.
Prior to the war, two of the brothers, John William Jones (1855-1858) and Francis Pendleton Jones (1859-1860) attended the University of Virginia. The collection is particularly interesting because one of the brothers was the Reverend John William Jones (1836-1909) who became a chaplain during the war, befriended General Robert E. Lee after the war and later wrote a famous civil war book, Christ in the Camp. The brothers often wrote to their mother, Ann Pendleton Ashby Jones (?- 1862 ), father, Francis William Jones (1811-1889) who was a store owner, their sisters, Helen Jones Sumner (n.d.), Page Jones Tucker (Willie Page) (n.d.) and Lute Jones (n.d.) and younger siblings at home. There are also letters from Reverend John William Jones to his wife, Julia Page Helm. (n.d.). The Jones family may be a relation of Brigadier General William Nelson Pendleton [1808-1883] and his son Colonel "Sandie" Pendleton.
The Reverend John William Jones was born in Louisa Court House, Virginia in 1836. He was ordained to the gospel ministry in 1860. He enlisted as a private in the Confederate Army after Virginia seceded in 1861. He was appointed regimental and then corps chaplain, earning the title of "The Fighting Parson". Jones witnessed hundreds of men profess faith in Christ in camps and hospitals throughout the war. After the war, while pastor of a church in Lexington, Virginia, he developed a close friendship with Robert E. Lee. The Reverend Jones edited the Southern Historical Society Papers for fourteen years, wrote several books on General Lee, and published Christ in the Camp in 1887. His express purpose for the book was that it 'would be useful in leading men to Christ and strengthen the faith and brighten the hope of true children of God'. Four of his five sons followed their father into the ministry. He died in 1909, greatly loved and respected as the 'most influential and well-known clergyman'... of the Lost Cause.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 154 letters of the Jones family from 1853-1908 in which 50 are original Civil War letters written by three brothers, John William Jones (1836-1909), Philip Edloe Jones (n.y.-1863) and Francis Pendleton Jones (1840 -1863) to their friends and family in Louisa Court House, Virginia. There are also ca.104 letters written before and after the war. One of the brothers is the famous Reverend John William Jones, author of Christ in the Camp. He corresponded with his family, his wife (Julia Page Helm) and other close friends (including Thomas Hume, Jr. and theologian scholar, Crawford Howell Toy).
From April to May of 1861, there are fourteen Civil War letters from Edloe Jones to his family where he described the details of camp life and his "perfect reconciliation" with it. He wrote that even though there is poor fare, little sleep and miles of marching he believes he could become really fond of this sort of life.
From June to July of 1861, there are eighteen Civil War letters from the Jones brothers to their family showing the closeness of the brothers as well as some friendly competition between them. There are also descriptions of fighting in Romney, and Martinsburg, Virginia with Stonewall Jackson. There is a letter from the Reverend John William Jones to his wife Julia Page Helm offering encouragement to be strong in bearing their separation. Another letter from Pendleton Jones to his sister, Lute, reveals some of the rumors going around camp suggesting a defeat of General Winfield Scott which he strongly believed to be untrue.
From August through December of 1861, there are fifteen Civil War letters from the Jones brothers that describe Civil War Generals, details of skirmishes, and glimpses of their harsh living conditions including a letter about a skirmish after the Battle of 1st Manassas and before Munson Hill.
In 1862, there are six Civil War letters from the brothers that convey a change in attitude toward the war. The brothers seem weary and disheartened at the prospects of anything good coming out of it. Edloe Jones is seriously injured and sent home where he dies after several months.
There are four Civil War letters from the Jones brothers in 1863, including a letter from the Reverend John William Jones to his wife about religion and the war. It reveals his strong will to minister to officers and soldiers so that their souls will be saved. There are also letters from Pendleton Jones that discuss politics in the campaign of the Governor of Virginia specifically regarding candidate William (Extra-Billy) Smith. The letters also contain a discussion of politics within the camp. The 13th regiment was re-organized and there were elections for captaincy and lieutenant and other positions. Pendleton wrote that he would probably be named Orderly Sargearnt
There are many officers generally mentioned throughout these letters including generals: Pierre Gustave Toutant Beauregard, Thomas Jonathan (Stonewall) Jackson, Robert E. Lee, Braxton Bragg, James Ewell Brown, (J.E.B.) Stuart, Joseph E. Johnston, James A. ['Old Pete'] Longstreet, Ambrose Powell (A.P.) Hill, James Alexander Walker, James Lawson Kemper, Richard Stoddert Ewell, Jubal Anderson Early, Nathaniel G. (Shanks) Evans, Robert Patterson, George Edward Pickett, Winfield Scott, Arnold Elzy (Jones), Earl Van Dorn, William (Extra Billy) Smith, George B. McLellan, Nathaniel Prentiss Banks, and John Charles "Pathfinder" Fremont. Other officers include Major James B. Terrill, Colonel Edward "Allegheny" Johnson, Captain H. W. Murray, Captain R. H. Anderson, Capt. Courtney, Colonel Gathes, Lieutenant Bird, Lieutenant Winston, and Seargeant John Hibbs.
The brothers fought and set up camp in some of the following places in Virginia: Harper's Ferry, Bolivar, Romney, Hanging Rock, Winchester, Martinsburg, Danville, Strasburg, Centreville, Rappahanock, Munson Hill, and Bull Run.
In Series II Other Jones family papers, there are 104 letters of the Jones family that were written before and after the war.
There are twenty-one letters from Francis William Jones to his son the Reverend John William Jones (1855-1859) while he was studying theology at the University of Virginia. Included is a letter that expresses his support for his son's chosen career.
There are also twenty-seven letters from Ann Pendleton Jones to her son, the Reverend John William Jones (1856-1859). She mostly wrote to him about local news regarding family and neighbors.
There are eighteen letters from Helen Jones to her brother the Reverend John William Jones (1853-1860). Among these is a letter from 1856 revealing that there were thirty cases of small pox in Charlottesville. Helen also wrote about students [drinking] making a fuss in town and being afraid of them. According to a letter titled Social Hall Monday morning she wrote, "There is to be a Temperance meeting in the hall tonight. I believe we are going but I am almost afraid to go there anymore. Dr. Broadus and Dr. McGuffey & several others are to speak this evening."
There is also correspondence between the brothers while they are at home and the Reverend John William Jones is at the University of Virginia and while he is visiting Greenville, South Carolina. Edloe Jones wrote to John on January 14,1860 about his studies. Pendleton Jones wrote three letters to John in 1859-1860.
There are two letters showing that Pendleton Jones was [temporarily] expelled from school before going to the University of Virginia.
Miscellaneous items include a photograph of Lieutenant Joe Berret- former Mayor of Washington and an original shoe shine cloth. There is also a clipping from the newspaper Atlanta Journal and The Atlanta Constitution on the former Washington Mayor and his appraisement and payment regarding emancipated slaves (Oversize folder).
There are also three letters from C. H. Toy (Crawford Howell Toy, 1836-1919) to the Reverend John William Jones. Toy was a close friend of John William Jones and was the famous Reverend and biblical scholar, who attended the University of Virginia with John. He spent time in Charlottesville teaching at the Albemarle Female Institute. He wrote to John in 1860 offering advice on difficulties with a certain deacon and how to direct his career. There are also six letters from another friend in theologian studies, Thomas Hume, Jr.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series: Series I.: Civil War letters from the Jones brothers; and, Series II.: Other Jones family papers. Series I is arranged chronologically and Series II is arranged by the last name of the sender and chronologically within each folder.
Contents List
- Series I: Civil War letters from the Jones brothers 1861-1863
  - Letters, 1861 April 5-May 31, 14 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Edloe Jones wrote letters to his mother, father, sisters Helen and Lute, including a letter dated June 6, 1861 where he wrote to his father after he first arrived in camp at Harper's Ferry, "There was a great rejoicing here tonight amongst the soldiers, at the success of the Baltimoreans over the Lincolnists... We have between 1,500 and 2,000 soldiers here and a good many more expected. It really looks like war about here now. Soldiers marching every which way, a cannon planted on the top of every neigboring hill."
  - Letters, 1861 June 5-July 30, 18 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Letters from the three brothers to their family including a letter dated June 6, 1861 where Edloe wrote to his sister about his brother, Pendleton, "Pen could bare more at camp than at University." (Harper's Ferry) In the same letter he also wrote "I saw an account of the fight at Fairfax C.H. in a dispatch sent to Billy Con. They speak of sending the Eastern Companies to Culpepper C.H. under Gen.(James Lawson) Kemper's command, but we are all violently opposed to it & do not think we will go..."
    On June 9, 1861 in another letter, Edloe wrote to his mother that the Captain is trying to get John the position of Chaplain. Sometimes his characterizations of camp life were humorous such as when he wrote about his brother's marching skills: "I pity the man's heels behind John". He also wrote about the Yankees, "If we do [fight] I will try to do my duty to kill one of the rascals at least if no more."
    On June 17, 1861 Edloe wrote a letter from Romney, Virginia showing that the brothers were very close and there was friendly competition between them. He wrote,"I was right amused at Pen, he disliked so much to give up before me, he was walking right by me, and he would ask me if I was not most broke down. I wd tell him not to wait for me, for I had no idea of giving up (and ride in the wagon)".
    On June 19, 1861 Pendleton wrote home to his father about fighting in Romney, Virginia, "There was a skirmish last night between our forces sent out on guard and some 150 federal troops. We took 2 pieces of cannon from them... Killed two of their men and took possession of and burnt the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Bridge at New Creek." He also wrote about his brother, "Ed is really in fare health and spirits. His merry peals of laughter daily echo throughout the campground. All our regiment is eager for an open fight with the enemy and sanguine that we can whip twice our number." John added a note at the bottom of the letter, "The Yankees ran like troopers and our men had to shoot them running."
    On June 27, 1861 John William Jones wrote to his wife Page (Julia Page Helm) from Camp Gibbons-near Winchester, with encouragement to be strong. He wrote, "Now, please, Dearest, for my sake as well as your own try and bear the separation better. It is indeed a sore trial for us thus to be separated from each other, and especially as our letters go so irregularly, but is our duty and you know that when we resolved to go 'far hence to the heathren' we made up our minds not to count trials when they beset the path of duty."
    On July 5, 1861 John also revealed in a letter to his sister that they were fighting with Colonel [Stonewall] Jackson near Martinsburg, "We soon hear tht Col. Jackson was engaging the enemy near Martinsburg and that we were wanted to support him. We expected to have made a forced march to Martinsburg that night but were marched into a field some six miles from Winchester where we camped for the night and made a leisurely march of ten miles to this place on the next day where we found Col. Jackson's command quietly awaiting us. On Monday we had a pretty smart skirmish with the enemy in wh, with greatly inferior forces, he repulsed them three times, took about 80 prisoners, killed upwards of a hundred, and then fell back to this place in good order, losing only one man killed, one missing, and five wounded. We (I mean the forces brought from Winchester 10,000 strong) immediately joined Jackson and our whole army was drawn up in line of battle expecting every hour an attack from the Yankees who were at Martinsburg in strong force. And thus we have been ever since- our men are not allowed to go far from their guns, we are ready and anxious for them to come, we have a very strong position-our artillery sweeps the approaches for two miles and if the Yankees wd only come we wd give them a threshing to which the fight at Bethel was mere child's play. But I don't believe the cowardly thieves are coming. They will content themselves with fortifying Martinsburg. We will have today a reinforcement of 3,000 or more (among them the N.O. artillery) and then we will be fully able to cope with them either here or at Martinsburg. But I doubt exceedingly whether we will have a fight- as soon as we move towards them I believe they will take their heels and recross the Potomac. Don't be uneasy about us. We are in the hands of a kind heavenly father who can preserve us..."
    On July 11, 1861, (Martinsburg) Edloe wrote a teasing remark about his brother Pendleton to his father, "I never saw a fellow eat as Pen does in my life. I can't begin to keep up to him."
    On July 26, 1861 Pendleton wrote to his sister Lute from Winchester about rumors circulating around camp. One rumor was that "Old fuss & feathers [General Winfield Scott] has been decapitated. How glad I'd be if now... having lost his first (only) grand battle he wd be dishonored by the federalists. Alexandria has been evacuated; that great consternation was caused in the Federal Capital by the defeat of Manassas; that old Abe has resigned, and that there is a general fight going on in the Metropolis. But these are mere fictions I imagine and resistance will be offered our invincible soldiers."
  - Letters, 1861 August 9-November 29, 15 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
    On August 31, 1861 Edloe wrote to his father from Camp Fairfax: (Skirmish after the Battle of 1st Manassas and before Munson Hill) "My dear Pa,I do not reckon Pen left me anything at all to tell about our march & fight the other day but I will write something about it even if I have to repeat what he has written... Well, about an hour before day on Sunday orders were given for one day's rations to be drawn, cooked & put in haversacks & to be ready to march with our blankets all day. Our Co. with the Montpelier Guard, The Baltimore Co. the Culpepper Minute Men & two pieces of the Newtown artillery under command of Major Terrel [James Barbour Terrill), commenced marching about half after six, we didn't know where we were going; after a march of nine or ten miles we came to Anondale, a little village, where we rested several hours. We started again at one, went two miles farther when we came to Chessnut [Chestnut] hill on Cap. Mason's farm, where we halted. We could see Washington & the Yankee pickets very distinctly. Col. [James Ewell Brown] Stuart with a part of his cavalry came to Chessnut hill soon after we arrived. Col Stuart took command of everything. Breastworks were laid off by Adjutant Blackford of Stewarts' [Stuarts'] cavalry, in front of Mason's house, & we commenced work about four oclock. I worked harder on that hill than I ever done in my life."
    "The Baltimore Co. were sent out to scout & they were fired upon by some of the Yankees in half a mile of us, they returned the fire & soon drove them off, took one prisoner up a tree. We stoped work abut eight oclock & went to sleep on the ground, but were aroused several times during the night by the firing of the pickets, their balls come very near us once & we all laid down on the ground to avoid them. We were at work again early the next day. We cd still see the yankee pickets on Munson's Hill & their scouting parties, some of which ventured very near to us, but a few shots at them from our men wd soon send them off in double quick time."
    "There was a school house, not over five hundred yards from Chessnut Hill, in the woods, wh the Yankees wd get behind & fire at our men, that house was burnt by our men. Not [a] single one of our men were hurt near Mason's hill, a horse belonging to one of the cavalrymen was shot through the leg; the loss of the enemy is unknown, but it is certain some were wounded if not killed."
    "We finished the fortifications late Monday evening. We were reinforced Monday night by a part of the Mayeland [Maryland] line & a part of a Georgia Regiment. Our blankets, overcoats & _____ were not back here Tuesday morning & our Co with the other three companies of the 13th, two pieces of artillery & two Mayaland Companies started for Munson's hill about eight oclock, we marched cautiously through the woods & got there in about an hour & a half, just before we got there we saw a yankee riding as hard as he cd down the road & we were ordered to shoot him; I didn't get a shot at him myself but some of our Co. did, his horse was shot & I think he was wounded. When we got on top of the hill we saw a body of Yankees drawn up at Bailey's Xroad, a mile off, we expected an attack. Four prisoners were taken in a peach orchard at the bottom of the hill. Our Co. with the Montpelier Guard commanded by Major Terrel went to Upton's house to search it, we found no Yankees but they had just left, they had not finished their breakfast, they left a bowl of soup & hot corn on the table. C.H. Upton is the rascal who pretends to represent Virginia in the Federal Congress & he is now in Washington."
    "Reinforcements arrived soon after the hill was taken. Our Co. was stationed at Upton's, a Baltimore Co. was sent up the road toward Loudon & Hampshire R.R., but were soon driven back, tow being wounded, they said the enemy were advancing upon us very rapidly. Major Terrel then ordered all of us to retreat to Munson's hill, we had not gone over a hundred yards before we met Col. Stuart who turned us back he said it wd never do for us to run. Our detachment (excepting the Culpepper M. M.) with two Mayaland Companies, making five Cos. in all, were led on, right after the Yankees, by Col. Stuart. We soon got in the woods & very near to the enemy, the skirmishes were put out to bring the battle on, the firing soon commenced, but it was some time before anyone but the skirmishes cd see a single yankee, not until we got to the Loudon & Hampshire RR., Then all of us commenced shouting, & the Yankees too sent up a shout, but their shouts didn't last long, for we charged across the R.R. upon them & you never saw such scampering in yr life, but they rallied again & for a few minutes their calls fell thick & heavy, They ran again across an open field & it was there that I got two fair shots at the rascals. We did not follow them anymore, but returned. I got three shots, don't know that I did them a great deal of harm, but think I struck one, for I had rest on the fence at him."
    "I was right near poor Robinson when he fell mortally wounded. The loss of the enemy is unknown, three were seen dead, I saw one fall; our loss in all the skirmishes were five wounded & one killed, we were certainly very fortunate. We were within two miles & a half of the chainbridge. When we got back to Munson's hill I was very much exhausted. I was not as much excited as I expected I wd be in my first fight, though I was right much excited until after the first fire. Col. Stuart as well as the men behaved very bravely, Col. S is as brave as he can be & is a splendid officer. Lieutenant Winston also conducted himself first rate, he kept as cool as a cucumber the whole time & gave his commands in a clear & distinct tone as if he was on the parade ground. Our Major showed a great deal of bravery & he raised himself in our estimation very much. I think he is most too rash."